I want to tell the people
of Barcelona, of Catalonia,
that I really thank you
for the warm welcome
you've given our army.
I'd also like the Spaniards to know
that it was a big mistake
to think that Catalans
were separatists,
and were against Spain.
I must say we have received
the most enthusiast welcome
I've ever seen,
and I have been lucky enough
to attend similar acts.
Nowhere, I tell you,
nowhere have we been received
with as much enthusiasm
and friendliness as in Barcelona.
BARCELONA (A MAP)
Have you come
to ask me to go again?
Actually, I've come to beg you
to leave.
Come in.
I wish I could give you something
worthy of your patience.
No, you don't owe me anything.
I'm sick and I can't afford
to pretend what I don't feel.
You can afford to be honest.
That's a very wild luxury.
What can I give you
that's worthy of you?
I know.
This photograph.
Come in.
Who is it? I don't know him.
Juan Rubio.
This picture was taken
as he danced over his mother's body.
After he'd killed her.
Why?
He was crazy, or lucid, who knows.
It was in the tabloids
a long time ago.
It's a gift.
I don't want it.
Don't reject my gift.
It's my only luxury.
Are you going to go?
I've always left before being asked.
I'm growing old.
Can I sit down?
How come we've never really talked?
People only really talk
when they're about to die,
and it's not usually interesting.
Are we really talking now?
I guess so.
Why can we today?
I have nothing to lose
and you're dying.
- Do you think I'm pitiful?
- No.
And do you think I am pitiful?
No.
This moment needs music.
Let's see if we get lucky.
La Bohème.
Do you know it?
I was a doorman at the Opera
for 35 years.
I retired the year it was burnt.
You must know who did it.
I wasn't there that day.
Isn't it weird that nobody was?
I don't know.
I don't like looking back.
I don't like looking forwards.
Is that why you hide?
I hide?
You hardly go out,
and if you do, it's at night.
Cities are more bearable
at night.
I take walks.
Sometimes I stop in front
of the buildings my son built.
I look for the open windows
which are lit
and watch the inhabitants
for a while.
No architect is brave enough
to do something like that.
Not even my son.
I can't sleep at night.
I'm scared of dying while sleeping.
And I dream a lot.
Lately I dream of the war.
The day the war finished, mostly.
Wars never finish, Ramon.
They just go on one after the other,
but don't finish.
Why did you turn it off?
When Callas sings,
nobody should talk.
Did you know I met her?
The year I started working
at the 0pera.
An admirer gave her a puppy
and it ran away in the Rambles.
She was desperate
when she got to the 0pera
and made me promise I'd find it.
I looked for it for over 2 hours,
but couldn't find it.
I shut myself in a closet
until she was gone.
I didn't want her to see me.
I can't stand disappointing people.
And me?
Doesn't it bother you to kick me out
after so long?
My wife and I want to spend
my last months on our own.
If I leave now,
I'll lose my last students.
You'll find more.
Don't be so sure.
People have lost faith in French
and God to the same extent.
If someone prays,
they do it in English now,
didn't you know?
I stopped believing in God
during the war, hearing the bombs.
The more the ruins,
the less I believed.
Praying would be hypocritical.
Why don't you teach English?
I'm not good enough
and I dislike it.
French...
French is very different.
I've even taught French in bars,
when I had lots of students
and bars were a part of life,
not only somewhere
to drink and spend time.
I'm sorry I've never smoked
or drunk.
Something to blame my illness on.
I can't blame anyone.
Everyone I knew has died.
There's only my wife left.
Do you love her?
Rosa? Yes, very much.
Actually, when I met her
I was a bit scared of her.
Scared?
I'm glad I'm going to die
before her.
Alone, I wouldn't know
what to do.
And you must love Barcelona.
Yes, of course.
I've always lived here.
Sorry. The doctor told me
not to hold in farts or belches.
I need to know when you're leaving.
I need to know tonight.
It isn't easy to find
a place like this.
There are many rooms for rent.
Not where I can teach too.
And I want one with an lift.
That will give my students
one less reason not to learn French.
Why don't you rent a flat?
Can you imagine all this mess
in a whole flat?
No, this is enough for me.
Can't you stay with your son?
My son and I can't stand each other
for more than an hour.
I made the mistake of being
totally honest with him
and not hiding my faults.
He never forgave me.
The only thing we've got in common
is we feel like shouting when
we're in front of Sagrada Família.
Don't you like it?
You should ask.
If the Sagrada Família like us?
If I were it, I'd scream too
with all that's around me
and no way of escaping.
You could leave Barcelona.
I've been away for long periods,
but I always come back.
It's similar to any other
Western capital,
content and happy with itself.
If you like, I can help you
pack all this up.
No, I think I'll throw it all away.
The magazines too?
Every time I move, I say I'll throw
everything away, but I don't.
Nasti de Plasti.
Do you want it?
No.
I've never liked anything
enough to keep it.
My wife does. She's kept
a diary since she was a child.
After we got married,
she let me read it,
but I said it wasn't necessary.
She's never spoke of it since.
I wrote a book a long time ago.
Back then everybody wrote a book,
just one,
and then spent years saying
how difficult it was to write.
What kind of book? A novel?
A novel that's out of print,
as all the ideas it contained.
I wanted to write about ideas,
not feelings,
but people have always
preferred feelings.
And they're right.
Ideas end up expiring.
Feelings, even if they're pathetic,
never expire.
You don't write anymore?
My best quality is
to always retire on time.
I could give you a plot.
For a novel?
But you must promise not to
publish it before my wife dies.
It's interesting.
No, forget it.
It's silly. It wouldn't work.
- What?
- It doesn't matter.
You won't tell me.
No.
What a shame.
I've not heard anything
interesting in ages.
Everyone I know is too busy
to live something interesting.
And your students?
They're the busiest.
They want to learn enough French
to read travel guides
and expensive restaurant menus
in Paris
or Shanghai.
You shouldn't scold them.
Scold them?
Sometimes I hear you
from the sitting room.
What do you hear?
How you scold them.
I don't scold them,
we discuss things.
Some are my friends' children,
the ones I ran to Paris with
without any money
but lots of ideas.
Molière, Montaigne,
Voltaire, Diderot...
The first thing they want to learn
is the word merde,
but they're not interested
in when to use it.
That's why we argue.
You can't simply shout "merde"
when you step on a dog's turd.
I can't speak languages
and haven't travelled far.
I envy you.
Me? Why?
You can fart wherever you want.
I wouldn't if it wasn't
for the doctor.
Come with me tonight.
- Where?
- For a walk.
- For a walk?
- For a while.
- No, it's late.
- Just a little while.
- Why do you want me to go for a walk?
- Nothing in particular.
You find reasons to walk
while walking.
I walk very slowly and soon
get tired. We won't go far.
It doesn't matter.
I can't climb stairs,
and I don't want
to leave my wife alone.
Voici le soir charmant,
ami du criminel.
I have the feeling everything
I say lately, I've read somewhere.
I never read much.
I left school early to start working.
At the Opera?
No. That was later.
You must've heard a lot of operas.
Some bits. None completely.
- You have a good ear, then.
- Why?
You recognized La Bohème.
I didn't.
My wife said
it would be on the radio.
- Rosa does like opera.
- You don't?
When I met her I told her I did
and after getting married
I didn't dare tell her the truth.
And it's too late now.
Too late?
To tell her the truth.
I don't know.
I've never known
when to bite my tongue.
That's why I'm not invited anywhere.
From time to time
a divorced friend calls,
or someone feeling nostalgic.
I don't see anyone because
I don't want to pity them,
or worse, having them pity me.
Well...
Are you leaving tomorrow, then?
So soon?
Monday, then.
Monday...
It can't be after Monday.
Avalanche, veux-tu m'emporter
dans ta chute?
I'll help you pack everything,
if you want,
but remember to tell your students
not to come back here.
I think I'll ask them to go
and I'll spend some time
translating cookery and DIY books.
But I'll go back to French.
In the end, it's only vanity.
I like myself much better
when teaching French.
It's a photogenic matter.
It's like Juan Rubio.
I'm sure he was never
as photogenic as there,
dancing naked
over his mother's corpse.
Why did he undress completely?
To feel more authentic.
More authentic?
Isn't that
what getting undressed is?
I don't know.
Haven't you ever felt
the need to get undressed
just to be really looked at?
I don't think so.
Sometimes, at the Opera,
I hid and disguised myself.
I liked going
to the costume storeroom
and trying things on.
There were all sorts of clothes,
from every period.
If I'd been discovered,
they'd have fired me.
- Nobody ever saw you disguised?
- No.
Would you have liked so?
I don't think so.
Yes?
Can I come in, David?
Just a minute.
Come in.
Aren't you going out tonight?
No.
- My knee hurts.
- What's wrong?
I have to be x-rayed on Monday.
- Can't you play on Sunday?
- No.
- How did you get hurt?
- Running, on my own.
- Does it hurt?
- A little.
- Did you call your boss?
- Not yet.
Did you tell them you're moving
on Monday?
I can't leave on Monday.
I'll have to wait
till I find someone
to lend a hand.
- When are you leaving, then?
- I don't know.
Maybe next Friday.
Maybe?
There's a lot of stairs to climb.
It makes me nervous to have
a gun in the house.
- It's unloaded.
- That doesn't make a difference.
- Won't they miss the gun?
- I'll take it back.
Aren't you afraid they'll fire you?
I'll probably leave before.
They're short of staff,
but don't pay well.
Why don't you call your wife?
My wife?
She might help you move.
We haven't talked in a long time.
She's with someone else.
Ataxi driver.
I thought I might catch his cab,
have him drive and
instead of paying him, pulling
the gun out and scaring him some.
Get out.
- What you doing?
- Get the fuck out!
Are you crazy?
What are you doing?
Shut up you cunt!
- Were you going to do it tonight?
- No, not tonight.
And the volume?
I turned it off.
It's Barça, isn't it?
It's an old game.
I cant' stand commentators,
they know nothing about football.
I can't see you.
Who?
Aren't you playing?
I never made the first team.
We both said we'd go and see
you play, but we haven't yet.
You play for Europa FC, right?
No. Júpiter.
Júpiter.
I won't forget, now.
Your room's very tidy.
I've never seen it like this.
Did you hear all the noise today?
When it's not Gaudí year,
it's Dalí, or something else.
So much noise makes me nervous.
You know, I've never been
to the top of the Sagrada Família.
I haven't been to a museum
or an exhibit in years.
When I was young, museums were empty,
there weren't any guards,
anyone could steal a picture
and bring it home.
- Most museums are still empty.
- Really?
People would rather rob
a shopping mall.
That's where most people go.
Do you work at a mall?
I keep changing.
- Do you have a lot of work?
- Too much.
The richer the rich get, the more
scared they are of being robbed.
Did you see my husband?
Yesterday. We talked.
What did he say?
He asked when I was leaving.
Three times.
- I went to a bullfight today.
- What?
I used to date a boy who liked it,
and took me to see them.
I never told my parents,
they wouldn't have let me.
I'd never been back till today.
- Did you like it?
- Not at all.
I left before it was over.
It's natural they're closing down.
Have you ever stopped doing something
for no reason?
Such as forgetting were
you stopped reading,
and never picking the book up again.
If I'd had sisters, I could see
how they're doing,
and know if I've been wrong or not.
I've never missed
not having brothers.
My father wanted a boy badly,
and when he saw I was a girl,
he completely ignored me
and hid in his factory.
For years, as a little girl,
I wanted to be a boy
for his sake,
and when I accepted
I'd never be one,
I dreamt someone
would burn the factory down
and my father would pay
some attention to me.
Then my brother was born.
And your mother?
She was completely useless.
When she got married,
she disappeared.
She walked around the house
afraid of stepping on the floor.
She did everything my father said
and soon I didn't respect her.
People only respect what they fear.
You can also respect
what you admire.
- Did you admire your father?
- No.
I just loved him.
I've only admired some
football players,
but not anymore.
- Football is getting boring.
- Why do you watch it, then?
It's the only thing
I know a lot about.
I know when they're playing well,
who's good and bad.
Is this match good?
It's not bad.
They've edited out the parts,
when nothing happens.
I wish you could do that with life.
What?
Editing out the periods
when nothing interesting happens.
There would be nothing left.
How old are you?
Thirty one.
I'm 76, but I'd like to be
40 less.
36 is the perfect age
for a woman.
It's not too young
nor too old.
There's still time to change,
to do something new.
And for a man?
I don't know, I'm not a man.
- I'd say 15.
- So young?
That was my perfect age.
It's too early to know.
What you should do
is find a job you really like
and try to keep it.
I always have the feeling
someone else could do it better.
There's always someone better.
In football,
when someone's better,
he plays and you don't.
But football is not life.
That's what my wife said.
No, she said it the other way round.
Life is not football.
She's probably with someone
better than me.
The taxi driver?
And you.
Maybe you've found someone better
and you're kicking me out.
I already told you
you had to leave.
I could stay in the first room
and you wouldn't see me.
If you have to hide,
it's not worth staying.
- You could pretend I'd left.
- I can't pretend I can't see you.
Who's winning?
In the old games Barça always wins.
My father supported Barça.
He went to the stadium
every Sunday.
Even after going bankrupt,
he kept going.
It was as if nothing had happened.
The whole stadium
is an ovation
we're the red and blue
it doesn't matter
where we come from,
be it South or North
we all agree, now,
we all agree
a flag makes us
brothers and sisters
Barça!
Why don't you change channels?
What would you like to watch?
I can't stay, I have stuff to do.
Stay a bit longer.
It's late.
Just a little while.
Wouldn't you rather sleep?
I'm not tired.
I haven't had dinner yet.
Please, stay.
Just for a minute.
Ok.
I'll stay for a minute.
Take a seat.
My husband is very late.
Are you scared he won't come back?
Why shouldn't he?
I don't know.
Do you know I met my husband
at the Opera?
It was raining and my cousin and I
were waiting for a cab.
He saw we were so bored
he told us how he had met Callas.
She'd lost a puppy on the Rambles
and he'd found it.
Your husband asked me to show him
how to load the gun.
- You put the bullets in here?
- I don't have any.
Let me, let me.
He's more scared of guns than me.
I'm used to them.
Have you ever shot a gun?
Not really.
My grandfather had one.
He bought it for the Tragic Week.
He was afraid his employees
would lynch him.
The gun ended up in a closet
and my cousins and I played with it.
- Do you know how to load it?
- No, and I don't want to.
Nobody wants a gun close by,
but everybody wants
their money protected.
Between the van and the safe,
not even one note can be missed.
I didn't know you did banks too.
You can stand a truncheon at home,
but a gun is too much.
Your husband isn't such an hypocrite.
My husband's ill.
You'd better leave him alone.
When I rented the room,
I thought you wanted a guard
so you wouldn't be scared at night.
You're never home, now.
My bosses think I live with my mum.
They don't like guards
who live alone,
or have marital problems.
They think you live with your mum?
At the beginning you treated me
as if I was your child.
You were willing to come see me play
on Sunday morning.
It's good you didn't come.
Until you came, I didn't know anyone
who liked football,
not even my dad.
He said he went to the game,
but he went to a whorehouse.
We all knew, at home.
Going to the game meant whores.
Maybe your husband went
to one today.
Did I hurt you?
I can't be your mother.
I've already had a daughter.
Where is she?
She died in the most stupid way.
She was run over by a bus
on Passeig de Gràcia long ago.
0ne of those which went
in the wrong direction,
they killed a lot of people.
Ramon almost went crazy.
Was this her room?
My daughter's?
Yes.
- You'd better go to sleep, now.
- I can't.
- Does your knee hurt?
- I've got insomnia.
Would you like a tablet?
Ramon has many.
Don't leave yet.
Stay until I fall asleep.
I'll stay
until you close your eyes.
Lie down.
No, don't turn it off.
- Do you sleep with the TV on?
- Yes.
You know what's worst
about working nights?
What?
The last hour before finishing.
It's the longest, and when
you hear the strangest noises.
The rest of the night
the noises are normal,
but then you hear things
you haven't heard before,
as if your hearing
could pick out everything.
Even people.
Voices of people who are not there.
I sometimes hear voices too,
but I don't listen to them.
When I hear them,
I start singing.
Singing?
Close your eyes.
I can't.
Of course you can.
Don't leave yet.
I'm not leaving.
Sono andati?
Fingevo di dormire
perché volli con te sola restare.
Ho tante cose
che ti voglio dire,
o una sola,
ma grande come il mare,
come il mare
profonda ed infinita...
Sei il mio amore
e tutta la mia vita.
Are you alright?
Yes, excuse me.
I fell asleep.
- No, no, don't get up.
- Sit down.
- You must be very tired.
- Thanks.
It's ok, leave them there.
Shouldn't you stop working now?
I'm working while I can.
I'm very slow now,
like a tortoise.
What happened?
Fuck!
They sharpened the knifes
and I cut myself, but it's nothing.
Were you waiting for me?
Yes, but I fell asleep,
I'm sorry.
Nice slippers.
Do you like them? They were a gift.
This too.
The best Spanish invention.
Too bad I can't use it at work.
We have a fan which only
messes up our hair.
Summer here is unbearable.
Really?
Do you need any help on Monday?
Monday?
To move out.
No, it's ok.
Some friends said they'd come.
The same ones
who didn't come last time?
They're doing me a favour.
It's hard at the wholesale market.
They load trucks all night.
So much food is wasted here.
It makes me sick.
Why don't they ever collide?
The fishbowl is so small.
As I can't tell them apart,
I didn't name them.
If your friends
can't come on Monday,
I can find someone else
to help you.
I didn't know you rented this place.
Didn't you?
No, your wife told me.
Yes, we always have.
I never talked to your wife much.
I realised lately
that when pregnant
people open their hearts to you.
What else did she say?
She asked if I'd come
to visit you.
Really?
But I'm not sure she meant it.
I said I'd call before coming.
She also asked if I had friends
in the neighbourhood.
We used to know all the neighbours,
but now
we don't even know
who lives next door.
So your wife said.
Now that I'll have more time,
I'm going to learn Catalan.
You can speak to me in Catalan,
so I can get used to it.
But you won't understand.
I understand everything
at the restaurant,
though I hardly leave the kitchen.
You know, the funniest word,
for me, is escamarlà.
Escamarlà.
Yes, escamarlà.
Are you going to keep working
at the restaurant?
Where else could I work?
Nobody's offered better.
A few days ago, a woman stopped me
in the street
to ask whether I wanted
to work for her.
I thought it was strange,
because I'll be useless soon.
So, casually, I asked some questions.
You know what she wanted?
She wanted my baby when I had it.
She didn't put it that way,
but I could see what she meant.
You must be careful now
with the baby.
You can't get distracted.
Especially when crossing
the street,
always check both ways.
You said exactly the same thing
when I moved in.
Really?
I thought you wanted to distract
me from the size of the room.
I didn't think you'd stay so long.
Neither did I.
But it stuck to me like a shell.
If you're staying,
you'd better sit.
At least the bed is comfy.
Yes.
Look into my eyes.
- Don't do the same as everyone else.
- Who?
Here, for someone to look you
in the eye, you have to fall down.
Did you fall?
No, but sometimes
I feel like falling,
just so they'll help me to stand
and ask if I'm ok.
You have to be careful now
with the baby.
You've already said that.
What would you name the baby?
I don't know.
What if I named it
escamarlà?
Just kidding.
Of course.
I also asked your wife.
- What did she say?
- She didn't know.
When you don't want to answer,
you say you don't know or viceversa.
If you like,
I'll think of a name and tell you.
- You won't.
- lf I think of one, I will.
You never asked about the father.
I thought you would tell us
if you wanted to.
And if I said it was yours?
Mine?
You must have thought about it.
It was only once,
and I'm sick...
If it wasn't for you, I don't know
what I'd have done.
I was very sad, too.
I'd been sacked without pay.
You didn't tell me.
I thought you did it
because you felt sorry for me.
That, too.
I won't kid you.
I thought of having an abortion,
all my friends said
I should have one,
because you're old
and the baby could have problems.
But I decided to have it,
with the baby
I wouldn't feel so alone.
Did you tell my wife?
What? That it's yours? What for?
I don't know.
- Has your wife ever eaten anyone?
- Sorry?
- Have you ever seen her eat anyone?
- No.
Why are you so scared of her?
I'm not scared of her.
I just don't want
to make her worry more.
She is really worried about you.
I'll leave the bowl for you.
No, take it, it's yours.
Don't feed them too much,
or they'll die.
Have you thought of which hospital
you'll go to?
Why do you ask?
Just because.
You were never interested before.
When you get here,
I'm usually in bed.
You waited for me today, though,
just to tell me to hurry up
and pack my stuff.
I guess your wife sent you.
No.
Well, yes,
because she had to go out
and I wanted to know you're fine.
You can see I am.
Yes.
Are you fine?
I get tired quicker than before,
but I'm fine.
- Does it hurt a lot?
- No, not a lot.
I'm scared it will hurt
when the baby is born.
I have never felt real pain,
not even a toothache.
I don't know if I'll stand it.
Of course you will.
Maybe not.
During the war,
I thought I wouldn't stand it,
but I did.
I told you not to talk
about the war or dead people.
I was just going to talk about...
At home everybody talked
about dead people.
All day, all night.
There's nothing worse than
the smell of a wake.
That's true.
When you're a kid,
you can run out and play,
but when you grow up,
you have to go farther away.
Nobody should be made to go
to a wake.
Did I say I was forced to?
Did I?
Waiting on hours of traffic,
that's what I'm forced to.
Working in a kitchen
being hot all day,
that too is an obligation.
That's true.
Don't just say I'm right,
like you do with your wife.
I'd rather you argued.
Why don't you argue?
There's nothing to argue about.
Then shut up.
I'm sorry, I didn't mean that.
But sometimes it's better to argue
than to say yes to everything.
That's true.
You're hopeless.
Should I leave?
Your wife
asked for my new address,
but I didn't give it to her.
Well.
When you start asking,
you want to know more and more
until it's a complete mess.
Yes.
You know?
Where I come from,
women who ask and tell the truth
remain alone for life.
I've never told the truth
and I've never been alone.
It's not the same with men.
Men always have
some woman or other.
Do you always tell the truth?
I was never so brave.
Let's do something.
I'll ask something
and you ask something back.
What for?
To tell the truth.
All the truth?
Yes.
What do you want to ask?
No, you first.
No, I'd rather you went first.
All right.
Why didn't you tell me
the baby was mine before?
You waited for me tonight.
If you had waited before,
I would have told you then.
That's why?
I never thought
of asking for money.
If not, I would've told your wife.
- Can I ask now?
- Yes.
No, it's embarrassing.
Go ahead and ask.
Why do you dress up as a woman?
You left your door open
and I almost went in.
When I worked at the Opera
I sometimes dressed up
in opera costumes,
and I still do that sometimes.
As a woman?
When you dress up,
it's like being someone else.
As if the costume
gave you something
you are not.
Do you understand?
Yes, I sometimes dressed up
in carnivals.
No, no, no.
I do it at home, just for me.
The dress wasn't very nice.
I know.
I could help you
find another one.
No, it's not necessary.
- Did you choose that one?
- Yes.
Didn't they ask
who it was for at the shop?
No.
I would have asked. You see?
That's why I'm alone.
Will you tell someone?
- Does your wife know?
- Yes.
What did she say?
Nothing.
Wait.
Lie down.
What for?
It's not enough just to dress up.
What do you mean?
Lie down.
No.
Don't move.
Have you ever tried it?
No.
You wash your face
before bed, don't you?
Yes, but it's very late.
It'll only take a second.
- Did I scare you?
- No.
Who opened the door?
Someone was going out
and I went in.
- I'll give you a key.
- It's not necessary.
What are they doing upstairs?
Wasn't that an earthquake?
There are no earthquakes in Barcelona.
There never have been.
You look tired.
No.
Have you had dinner?
At the hospital.
In front of 4 anorexic girls
I'm teaching how to eat.
Anorexia overwhelms me
and fascinates me.
Fascinates you?
- Do you remember today's lunch?
- Yes.
And yesterday's?
And the day before's?
They remember every crumb
we make them swallow.
One of them said today
that people look at her
as if she were a pig
being fed to be slaughtered.
She might be right.
Might she?
You know why I became a surgeon?
To look for the soul.
I never found it.
It wasn't there.
You thought you'd find it
operating?
There are extraordinary things
in the human body.
Why couldn't the soul be there?
Why couldn't it be tangible
like kidneys or intestines?
Religion and psychiatry
haven't been able to show the soul.
And they've had time enough,
especially religion.
I went to a bullfight today.
Most of the audience
were foreigners.
After the second bull,
they supported the bulls
instead of the bullfighters.
And you?
I left before it was over.
Then I walked to the old train station.
Remember, I took you there
as a kid
to see the trains come and go?
Yes, I do remember.
When did you last catch a train?
A long time ago.
Where did you go?
To Venice.
Venice?
First to Milan, then Venice.
That's where I first saw colours.
Which colours?
All of them.
What colours can you see now?
Black and white.
Just that?
The last time I saw them
was during the Olympic Games.
I was a volunteer.
Everybody was euphoric,
athletes parading
and the audience applauding.
Then I took my trousers off.
- You did?
- Yes.
I can never tell when you'rejoking.
I'm always serious.
I never understood
why you volunteered.
They needed doctors,
and the psychiatrist told me
It'd help me come out of myself.
- Do you still go?
- Not anymore.
Endogamy is incurable, sister.
You can tell by looking
at the upper class families left.
Why did you call?
I hadn't heard from you
in a long time.
Do you remember the last time
we talked?
No.
Ramon is really ill. Did you know?
You told me.
Do you know who's singing?
No.
Callas.
I never got you to like opera,
or to go to there with me.
Do you still go?
Not anymore.
It's expensive, and going alone...
If you like we can go.
I'll pay.
Would you go with me?
- On one condition.
- What?
- Afterwards, we set it on fire.
- The Opera House?
They'd build another one.
We should burn something else.
The Agbar Tower, for instance.
And we wouldn't leave it at that,
then we'd burn...
the MACBA.
And then?
If they don't stop us,
there are some skyscrapers
which would burn wonderfully.
Don't forget the National Theatre.
And the Sagrada Família.
It's not finished,
but we could burn it.
And Catalunya Square.
And Passeig de Gràcia.
Once it was burnt down,
I'd plant a vineyard,
as a homage to phylloxera,
which made it possible.
Why did you call?
I wanted you know how you're doing.
That's all?
We've kicked out the tenants.
They're all leaving next week.
You wanted to tell me that?
We thought it would be best
to be alone.
What for?
Ramon wants to die at home.
- Is he sure?
- Yes.
- It'll be difficult for the both of you.
- We know.
If you're really sure,
it's fine by me.
Will you come if I call you?
Why?
He said he wants
to ask you something.
- Me?
- Yes.
Why doesn't he ask his doctor?
- He wants to talk to you.
- I'm not an oncologist.
It's nothing to do
with the illness.
What is it?
He didn't want to tell me.
It must be a man thing.
Man thing?
He must be embarrassed to tell me.
Lately he's just talked about the war,
the day it ended.
He'd better talk to his doctor.
You won't come, then?
I don't know.
If you come,
I'll let you read my diary.
- You still keep one?
- Yes, I do.
- Everyday?
- Almost.
Can I read it from the start?
Yes.
- Will you come?
- Show it to me now.
- No. Next time you come.
- I want to read it now.
I'll give it to you
if you read it after you leave.
Can I take it with me?
Yes.
Where is it?
In that drawer.
I've always been scared
of people who lock things.
It's the only locked drawer
in the house.
Father locked everything.
Do you remember?
The green is the oldest.
This one?
Yes.
"Dad came to my room tonight..."
- Has anyone else read it?
- No.
- Not even your husband?
I'd never seen your writing.
I told you not to read it here.
Don't you go to the hairdresser's?
I don't get out much.
Why?
I even have food delivered.
- Do you have enough money?
- Yes.
And when he dies?
What?
You'll only have half of his pension.
I'll get by.
- Will you look for new tenants?
- I don't know.
If you need any money, let me know.
You're always broke.
I wish we were rich, like before.
Yes.
Can I comb your hair,
like I did as a child?
Your hair was long and I combed it.
I thought I'd have it cut.
No, don't. I won't let you.
- Where's the comb?
- In the bathroom.
- Go get it.
- No.
- Then I'll come again and take you.
- Where?
To the hairdresser's.
We could go to the hairdresser's
and then the Opera.
Would you like that, sis?
Are you ok? You're shaking.
I'm fine.
Don't you want it?
I'll take it some other day.
- It's late. Stay for the night.
- I have to go.
I'll bring some sheets and
you can sleep on the settee.
It's hot here,
and someone's waiting for me.
- Who?
- Someone, in the street.
- Did you come with someone?
- It's someone I don't know yet,
someone I'll know tonight
and who'll explain everything.
Everything?
I won't find that person here,
or in Barcelona.
I'd have to go farther.
Why don't you leave, then?
I thought you'd leave before
and tell me about it.
Me?
Why did you take me
to the train station, then?
To see other people leave?
- Are you dating someone?
- No.
I thought
I'd found someone tonight.
Who?
- A very handsome boy.
- What happened?
I took him home and,
as I fixed the drinks
and thought of things to say
so as not to go straight to bed,
he fell asleep.
What did you do?
Nothing.
- You didn't wake him up?
- No.
- You left him home alone?
- Yes.
What if he wakes up and you're gone?
I want to go home
and find him gone.
What if he's still there?
Then I'll kill him,
and I'll be in the papers tomorrow,
then I'll go to jail
and you'll come to visit me.
Will you visit me in prison?
I think you won't.
Your hands are beautiful.
You should have been a pianist.
Why do you always
change the subject?
I regret not seeing you operate.
I'm sorry you married someone
without an imagination.
We're even.
No, we're not.
Come on, come with me.
Where?
- Let's go far away tonight.
- I can't go anywhere.
Pack and let's go.
And your job?
Fuck my job. Let's go.
- I can't.
- Of course you can.
And leave him here, ill?
Yes, it's true.
Now you have to play
the good Samaritan.
That's my second slap tonight.
I can tell you've practiced.
- I've never hit you before, have I?
- No.
It was the first time.
Did I hurt you?
Good night, sis.
It's too much, isn't it?
Maybe the eyes.
- I'll wash it off.
- No, don't.
- And the dress?
- It's not bad.
Really?
- And the wig?
- Not tonight. It's too hot.
- The lips.
- No, leave them.
What are you doing?
- I'll show you how to load it.
- Why?
Didn't you want to know?
Is it the guard's gun?
He lent it to me.
There's no bullets, but it's ok.
You open it like this.
You put the bullets in,
you close it
and you fire.
Did the guard show you?
No. My father and grandfather did.
- Did they have a gun?
- Because of the reds.
During the war,
playing on the beach,
I found a gun in the sand,
but I couldn't touch it.
The older boys in the gang
took it away.
Come on, shoot.
- Why?
- Come on.
Promise never to ask for it again.
Ok.
All right.
Will you have your hair cut?
Yes.
That's a shame.
Not for me.
I met my brother.
- And?
- He'll come again.
Really?
Did I ever tell you that,
as a child, I wanted to be a boy?
I wanted to be a boy
and my brother a girl.
Your brother?
Do you find it strange?
No.
We both wanted to be Russians.
Russians?
To have a Russian soul, you know.
Not really.
Didn't you want to be
from somewhere else, as a kid?
I don't know, I can't remember.
What was your ideal age?
My what?
The best year you can remember.
The year the war finished, I guess.
That's not what I mean.
What do you mean?
It doesn't matter.
What do you think?
It's nice.
That's all?
You look younger.
Younger than who?
Than before.
What do you mean?
We're not similar at all.
We never have been.
It's enough that I dress up,
you don't need to.
I want to go with you.
Don't go alone.
I don't mind.
- You have to practice my signature.
- I know.
But you don't practice.
There's still time.
The government...
In two months I have to go
to the bank and sign again.
I've already told you.
We'll open an account
in a different bank
and I'll sign.
So when you leave,
I can still get your pension.
That's what you wanted, right?
Did you tell your brother?
No.
What did you tell him?
Nothing.
And will he want to sign your
death certificate instead of mine?
I'm sure he will.
He doesn't like me.
He doesn't like anyone,
don't worry.
Where are you going?
I'm getting changed.
- No, wait.
- Why?
- I need to tell you something.
- What?
- I'm scared to tell you.
The Argentinean's baby is mine.
Yours?
It was only once,
the day I was told I had cancer.
You were not here
and I told her everything.
- When did you find out?
- She told me tonight.
What did you say?
I didn't know what to say.
- Did she ask for money?
- She doesn't want any.
- Didn't she ask?
- No, she didn't.
Did she say if
she'd bring the baby by sometime?
No, I don't think so.
Are you upset?
I also have to tell you something
I've never told you.
Because I was scared, too.
Of me?
Yes.
What is it?
My brother isn't my brother,
he's my son.
I don't understand.
I had him with my father.
He didn't make me do it,
I did it because I wanted to.
But you were very young.
He was the only one I loved.
Does Santi know?
I think so.
Anyway, I gave him my diary.
That's why you never showed me?
The diary?
You never asked.
Once you said you would,
but you didn't.
Really?
Can't you remember?
I'll give to you, if you want.
I want to give you something too.
This guide.
It's very old.
One of my first jobs
was to help make it.
Why is it underlined?
One very hot summer
I collected payments,
and I marked
all the shaded streets.
I thought the next summer
I'd go faster
and wouldn't be as hot.
But it wasn't much use,
I soon started working at the 0pera.
It's like a big map of shadows.
Passeig de Gràcia is not there.
I know.
I tore off all the pages
where you could see it.
These clothes are too warm.
And the shoes are tight.
- I'll take them to the cobbler.
- He closed down.
I'll find another one.
- My grandfather was a cobbler.
- I know. You told me.
- Do you know how he died?
- How?
Burnt.
Burnt?
0ne night, as he was sleeping
beside my grandmother,
he started to burn.
What do you mean?
His body started burning.
It's called spontaneous combustion.
That's impossible.
Nobody sets on fire spontaneously.
He was fatter than me,
and drank.
You haven't drunk in ages.
Besides, it's impossible.
Nobody sets on fire like that.
It's possible.
I know how to do it.
What?
Burning something
without touching it.
I can burn things, if I like.
You can?
Yes.
How?
Just thinking about it.
Thinking about it?
Look.
Can you see the handkerchief?
I've been thinking about it
getting warm for a while.
It will start burning
at some point.
- Are you serious?
- Yes.
No, don't touch it!
It doesn't seem to be burning.
It's hard, because it's damp.
And I'm out of practice,
I haven't tried in ages.
Have you ever burnt anything?
What?
At first it was only little things,
until one day
I wanted to see if I could
burn something bigger.
I got scared and stopped.
What did you burn?
The Opera House.
What?
I burnt the Opera House.
You're kidding, aren't you?
Do you actually think you burnt it?
Yes, I did.
You were at home, then.
I did it from here.
- It was burning earlier, right?
- No.
- How did it set on fire?
- I told you. It's me.
With your mind?
- Did you burn it like that?
- Yes.
But it was harder, it's farther.
Why did you burn it?
Everybody said
we needed a new Opera House.
More and more people started saying
they wished it'd burnt down
so they could build
a newer, bigger one.
So eventually, I did it.
I burnt it.
Have you ever told anyone?
No, I haven't.
I was scared of telling.
Even me?
Especially you.
We forgot about the opera.
It must be almost over.
What you said about Callas
is true, isn't it?
Of course it is.
What did she say
when you brought her dog back?
She thanked me.
I told you, didn't I?
That's all?
She was in a hurry and
just thanked me.
In Italian?
Yes, in Italian.
"Ti ringrazio."
I'm sorry.
Have you taken all your tablets?
Aren't you tired?
Not yet.
- And you?
- No, not yet.
It's very hot tonight, isn't it?
Do you need to go to the toilet?
Yes.
Go first, if you like.
Are you sure?
I'll wait.
I won't be long.
Are you going like that?
It's very late.
They'll be sleeping.
With Castilian loyalty
I'm proud to state
that 40 years of progressive
dehispanicisation
calls for an immediate
and continuous effort
in the opposite direction
to rehispanicise Catalonia,
into which I hope to put
all my efforts,
from kindergarten
to highest cultural levels,
the only real explanation
of many regretful
events and attitudes,
even in the seemingly farthest
areas of the spiritual sphere...